Guide to the Oscar Diedrich von Engeln papers, 1866-1965.
Engeln, Oscar Diedrich von papers, 1866-1965.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Oscar Diedrich von Engeln papers, 1866-1965.
14-15-856
O. D. von (Oscar Diedrich) Engeln, 1880-1965.
6.9 cubic ft.
Correspondence, notebooks, exams, manuscripts, clippings, scrapbooks, diaries, certificates, diplomas, family genealogy.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence pertaining to von Engeln's years at Cornell as a student and professor and to his writings on geology and Cornell history.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of geology, Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence pertaining to von Engeln's years at Cornell as a student and professor and to his writings on geology and Cornell history; student notebooks and exams; manuscripts of published and unpublished works; ice experiment notes by John L. Rich, 1911, later published by von Engeln, 1914; ice surface rubbings; "Records of Physiographical Experiments," 1915-1917; photographs of family, friends, colleagues and students, geological subjects, and world travels; von Engeln's camera; photographs of natural features in Turkestan taken by W. Rickmer Rickmers, with related correspondence; clippings; scrapbooks, diaries; certificates and diplomas; and a family genealogy. Material pertaining to Ralph S. Tarr, Professor of Geology, and reminiscences of other Geology Department members. Also, letters (including one from T. C. Chamberlin), unpublished articles, notes, two diaries, and photograph album (with identification) concerning Alaskan trips in 1906 and 1909.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Engeln, O. D. von, 1880-1965.; Chamberlin, Thomas C. (Thomas Chrowder), 1843-1928; Rickmers, Willi Rickmer, 1873-1965.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University. Dept. of Geology.
Subjects:
Geology.
Places:
Asia.; Ithaca (N.Y.); Alaska--Description and travel.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
BoxES 1, 9
Series II. Ralph S. Tarr Memorial
Box 1
Series III. Cornell and miscellaneous
Boxes 1, 8, 10, 18
Series IV. Writings
Box 1
Series V. Photographs
Subseries I. Family, friends, other
Boxes 2, 3, 4, 11
Subseries II. Greenland expedition
Boxes 2-3
Subseries III. Other expeditions
Boxes 4
Subseries IV. Negatives (some glass)
Boxes 5, 13, 14-18
Subseries V. Postcard albums
Box 6
Series VI. Scrapbook
Box 7
Series VII. Certificates and diplomas
Box 8, Mapcase Folder
Series VIII. Alaskan trips; 1906, 1909
Boxes 4, 9
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - William Dean Howell's letter, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and notes on Cayuga Rock Salt Company, 1919-1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from T. C. Chamberlin to Oscar von Engeln, June 24, 1914 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence regarding glacial lake history of the Cayuga Valley, 1933-1934 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Series II. Ralph S. Tarr Memorial
  - Ralph S. Tarr Correspondence, 1905-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Items pertaining to the death of Ralph S. Tarr, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ralph S. Tarr Memorial: correspondence, 1913-1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ralph S. Tarr Memorial: lists, letters, financial records, 1912-1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ralph S. Tarr Memorial: suggestions re inscriptions, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series III. Cornell and miscellaneous
  - Genealogy and related items, 1866-1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellany, 1891-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cornell items, 1904-1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Expenses of the Deaprtment of Physical Geography and Summer School Instruction (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pamphlets for Geology I, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Cornell University Summer Session Geography and Geology" (draft), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sigma Gamma Epsilon miscellany, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1902-1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Syllabus, c. 1905 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Ice experiments typescripts, rubbings, notebook, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Ice experiments typescripts, rubbings, notebook, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "Before Ithaca" Articles (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Broadside, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - History pf Cornell University Department of Geology, 1919-1938 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Cornell calendar, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Miscellany, Cornelliana (Box 8)
  - Book of Letters to von Engeln, 1948 (Box 8)
  - Diary, Mrs. von Engeln (formerly Maude Graham Hewitt), 1930 (Box 8)
  - Records of physiographical experiments, 1913-1917 (Box 8)
  - Gold stick pin, belonged to Prof. O.D. Von Engeln, oval outline with 2 narrow bars across the center, Sigma Xi, n.d.; MU-761 (Box 10)
  - Oval shaped pin with an open book and the words “The Cornell Lion”, gold inscription on back: “D. Von Engeln 1908”, Sigma Xi, MU-762 (Box 10)
  - Gold Sigma Xi key with “O.D. Von Engeln” on back, n.d.; MU-763 (Box 10)
  - Camera used by O. D. Von Engeln in Alaska, 1909, 1911; MU-1402 (Box 10)
  - Lewis B. Kelsey: term paper in Special Problems Geol. 208 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Miscellany (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Glacial Pebbles (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Glaciers (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Glaciers and Glaciation (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Series IV. Writings
  - Reports, Essays and Drafts (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Reports, Essays and Drafts, 1919-1934 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mss. by von Engeln, 1891-1936 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Finger Lakes Region - Mss. (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
  - Finger Lakes Region - Printed, c. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Finger Lakes Region - Galleys, c. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Principles of Geology, mss. foreword through chapter 3 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 4-8 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 9-11 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 12-13 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 14-16 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 17-18 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 19-21 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 22-24 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 25-26 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 27-29 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 30-32 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 33-36 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Principles of Geology, chapters 37-39 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Reminiscences, mss. pp 1-109 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Reminiscences, mss. pp 110-214 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Clippings, Reviews, 1934; 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Reviews and Advertisements, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
- Series V. Photographs
  - Subseries I. Family, friends, other
    - Photograph Albums (Box 2-3)
    - Family (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - Family and Other, 1906-1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Family and Other, 1906-1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Family and Other, 1910-1963 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Family and Other (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Family, 1903-1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Friends and Colleagues, 1908-1963 (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
    - Students, 1907-1952 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
    - Willard Straight Hall Party, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - New York State photograph album, 1920 (Box 11)
  - Subseries II. Greenland expedition
    - Photograph Albums (Box 2-3)
  - Subseries III. Others expeditions
    - Expeditions (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Geological Expeditions, 1904-1950 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Glaciers, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Ters-Agar (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - At Duwana (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Above Jailgan looking towards Tupchek (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Kalta-Karamk (just before Kizil-sn enters western gorge) (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Kalta-Karamk (eastern end of this broad section of Kisil-sn) (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - 1 map (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Kem-Kuban (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Darant-Kurgan Panorama E-S-W, Trans-Alai Range (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Obi-niob (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Approaching the Garmo Glacier (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - View from Farna-Kub above Pashimgan to Darvaz (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Panorama of Tupchek; the Gildi (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Glacier and its Moraines (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Peter the Great and Zerin-Zamin from Range of Little Tupchek (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Around Little Tupchek (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Top-Kurgan (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Subseries IV. Negatives (some glass)
    - Index for 3"x4" slides (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Negatives (Box 5)
    - Moraine look at Reynoldsville-Bennettsburg - one from Cayuta Valley from hill on Nicklesburg Road, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Moraine look at Reynoldsville-Bennettsburg - one from Cayuta Valley from hill on Nicklesburg Road, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Topographic sections of New York State on o/s glass negatives, two photocopies of prints of maps [unidentified], 19-- (Box 13)
    - Divide Area - obsequent and consequent streamheads near Candor - on Southside of Candor - Van Ecttem Valley - First road west of Candor, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Negatives of Oct. trip with Wold (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Jonet Face Univ. Quarty - Jonet Face of recok bing quarried for Taylor Hall University Quarry - bottom of east side of road, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Shows glacier sculpture (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Tully Falls - Lower Taughanic, 1933 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Crowbar Point, 1933 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Truncated Spur - west side of Six Mile Valley from Coddington Road, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Tributary Valley north of Bold Hill on east side of Six Mile Valley, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Up Valley at Sweden Valley, PA - looks NE to NE - no ice glacial, 1932 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Excursion to Divide area around Cayuta, also Moraine Channel near Newfield, Oct. (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Whitstone Gulf Butresses - This gorge is so large because eroded just glacially in very weak shales, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Overflow southward into Unadilla Creek Headwaters of high level lake founded in slope of esearpment, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Terrace along east side of outlet - highway crossing near junction with Pony Hollow, 1932 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Downstream toward Cayuta Outlet (south) Terrance on west side of lower end (from highway toward Pony Hollow), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Doubtful bedrock near divide, upheaved or transported? (lower gorge, near divide), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Place of divide, near position of photo above, looking downstream (lower gorge, divide), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Swamp at divide point looking south (lower gorge), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Ledge rock fall in tributary valley, NE side of gorge (above divides, lower gorge), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - View of north end of lower gorge toward SE, 1932 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - View of lower gorge valley from north end southward, hill in distance, flat area, winding, local waste, 1932 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Cayuta Gorge (middle) outlet - junction with lower gorge. (middle gorge outwashed at mouth, junction), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Upper Cayuta Gorge outlet north of junction with middle gorge (south of road bridge), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Fall hill east of which flows out outlet channel, head of middle gorge, west of which lies present outlet channel (along road about one mile north of Alpine), 1932 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Wattems (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Richford from Morainic Knoll looking west diagonal slide up Truncated Slope, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Truncated Spur and slightly modified Valley on east side of Horesheads Elmira, trough at Horseheads, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Cortland, NY - South of glacially scoured divide notch - see maps, also note - Virgical continuation of this valley, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Labrador Hollow - West end from summit of hill west of village, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Rock City, Olean-blocks of Olean conglomerate tilting down hill due to weathering Alleghany Plateau level to south and west, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Rock City, Olean - look NE surface of conglomerate and joints, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Moraine - Cross section Six Mile (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Fall Creek (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Newark Valley, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Near Headwaters of Chenango Creek, NY - view from road ro right leading up to 1761' elevation. This is on Taylor Valley region, south of Fulton, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Danby - looking down State Road toward East Notch and toward north wall of Danby Trough, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Six Mile Creek - Entrance bridge in park, 1917 (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Dunde Region - Pony Hollow and Jackson Hollow Saddle - SW of Newfield (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - Ithaca area and elsewhere (glass and film negatives, Cornell University Geology Dept. staff (film negatives (Box 15)
    - Malloryville esker (glass negative), Malloryville kames (glass negatives), field notes, Ithaca area photographs, c.1928 (Box 16)
    - Photos and slides: local (film negatives, West India (glass negatives), Iceland (film negatives) (Box 17)
  - Subseries V. Postcard albums
    - Post Card Albums (Box 6)
- Series VI. Scrapbook
  - Student Scrapbook (Box 7)
- Series VII. Certificates and diplomas
  - American Geographical Society Fellow, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - American Geographical Society Life Fellow, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Corporal, New York, State 4th Infantry, Company D, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. von Engeln, preparation of Red Cross surgical dressings instructor, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. von Engeln, Woman's Committee for Fifth Liberty Loan, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Acknowledgement of Mrs. von Engeln's service with the Fifth Liberty Loan, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Red Cross Membership, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - von Engeln elected a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science Fellow, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Recognition of Mrs. von Engeln's services with the Red Cross, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica contributor, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Cornell Geological Society membership, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Maude Graham Hewitt, academic diploma from Margaretville, N.Y., High School, 1904 (Map-case Folder)
  - Maude Graham Hewitt, high school diploma, Margaretville, N.Y., High School, 1904 (Map-case Folder)
  - Maude Graham Hewitt, advanced academic diploma, Margaretville, N.Y., High School, March-June 1905 (Map-case Folder)
  - Oscar von Engeln, B.A. from Cornell University, 1908 (Map-case Folder)
  - Maude Graham Hewitt, B.A. from Cornell University, 1909 (Map-case Folder)
  - Marriage certificate of von Engeln and Maude Graham Hewitt, 1910 (Map-case Folder)
  - Oscar von Engeln, Ph.D. from Cornell Unievrsity, 1911 (Map-case Folder)
  - Maude Graham Hewitt, initiation certificate from Delta Zeta Sorority, 1919 (Map-case Folder)
  - Association of American Geographers membership (Map-case Folder)
  - Paper designating von Engeln United States delegate to the international Geographical Congress, held in Warsaw beginning Aug. 23, 1934 (Map-case Folder)
- Series VIII. Alaskan trips; 1906, 1909
  - Cornell and Alaska Expeditions, 1896-1909 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Cornell exploring party, 1906; 1909 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Unpublished articles, notes, two diaries, and a photo album concerning Alaskan expeditions, 1906, 1909 (Box 9)